Finding aid to the Katherine Elizabeth McClellan Papers CA.MS.00141
Smith College Archives
Katherine Elizabeth McClellan Papers
1878-1996
1904-1918
Smith College Archives
McClellan, Katherine Elizabeth
CA.MS.00141
8.875 linear feet (9 containers)
The Katherine Elizabeth McClellan Papers contain biographical information, newspaper clippings, a small amount of correspondence, a scrapbook and photographs documenting McClellan's career as a professional photographer in Saranac Lake, New York, Northampton, Massachusetts, and later Sarasota, Florida.
Biographical / Historical
Katherine Elizabeth McClellan (1859-1934) was born and raised in Paterson, New Jersey. After graduating from Smith College in 1882 she worked for eight years in private schools and as a tutor in New York and New Jersey. Her career as a photographer began in the Adirondacks in 1892 when the McClellan family moved to Saranac Lake, NY so that Katherine's sister could be treated for tuberculosis at the Adirondack Cottage Sanitarium. Katherine McClellan took up photography as a hobby, concentrating on landscapes. She turned her hobby into a thriving business. In addition to selling her photographs, McClellan also published two viewbooks, John Brown, or A Hero's Grave in the Adirondacks (1896) and Keene Valley: "In the Heart of the Mountains" (1898), and planned two more Saranac Lake and Lake Placid. It is not known whether these two were ever completed.
In 1903 McClellan started spending part of the year in Northampton, Massachusetts. She opened a studio on State Street and announced in the Smith College Monthly magazine that she 'was reading to take all order for photographs.' A large share of her business came from the college. She was hired to make photographs to illustrate college publications and newspaper and magazine articles. The College also called on her to document physical changes on campus. Her views of buildings, classrooms, the campus, and special events highlighted the College's facilities while presenting a dignified image of education and life at Smith. In 1912 she was given the title "Official Photographer of Smith College."
McClellan also produced for the College yearbook portraits of students and faculty, and group photographs of club members and house residents. She also documented the activities and events of college life such as dances, proms, and dramatic productions. In addition to her work for the College she also took portraits of local people, visiting dignitaries such as Helen Keller, Julia Ward Howe, and Henry James, to mention a few. She also took images of local townspeople.
In 1918, at the age of 59, McClellan retired to Florida. She and her sister, Daisietta McClellan, developed a tract of land known as McClellan Park and McClellan continued to make photographs of the Florida landscape and its people. On her move to Florida, McClellan sold her studio to her collaborator of ten years, Eric Stahlberg. He continued to shoot images for the College through the late 1940s and sold images, negatives and films to the College in 1958. Katherine McClellan died in Sarasota in September of 1934.
Scope and Contents
The Katherine Elizbeth McClellan Papers contain biographical information, newspaper clippings, a small amount of correspondence, a scrapbook and photographs documenting McClellan's career as a professional photographer in Saranac Lake, New York, Northampton, Massachusetts, and later Sarasota, Florida.
Photographs include images McClellan took of the Smith College campus in 1904. The photographs are arranged in alphabetical order by name of building and include interior and exterior shots. In 1912 McClellan took a series of images of the Hillyer Art Gallery and these images are included with this series. McClellan was noted for her photographic landscape work and the collection includes images from the Adirondacks and Florida. Also included are images of her studio at 44 State Street in Northampton, a number of self-portraits and images of family and friends.
Related Material
Additional images taken by Katherine McClellan as the official photographer at Smith College may be found in a wide array of records of the College. An inventory of her photographs in other portions of the College Archives is available on site.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Katherine Elizabeth McClellan Papers were donated to the Smith College Archives by McClellan in 1918. Photographs by McClellan have been donated over time to the Archives by various individuals. Original prints and glass plate negatives were donated by her long-time business partner, Eric Stahlberg and his widow.
McClellan, Katherine Elizabeth
- Biographical Material, 1892-1996 (Box 935, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Newspaper clippings, invitations, photocopies of advertisements, and photographs
- Correspondence, 1908-1918 (Box 935, Folder 2)
- Publications: John Brown, or A Hero's Grave in the Adirondacks, 1896 (Box 935, Folder 3)
- Publications: Keene Valley: "In the Heart of the Mountains", 1898 (Box 935, Folder 4)
- Publications: Twelve Months in the Adirondacks, 1899 (Box 935, Folder 5)
- Photographs: Smith College Series A-L, 1904 (Box 935.1)
- Photographs: Smith College Series M-Z, 1904 (Box 935.2)
- Photographs: Smith College Hillyer Art Gallery, 1912 (Box 935.3)
- Photographs: Adirondacks and Florida Landscapes, undated (Box 935.4, Box 935.5)
- Photographs: Non-Smith Dramatics (Box 935.7)
- Photographs: Studio, 1903 (Box 935.6)
- Photographs: Self Portraits, undated (Box 935.6)
- Photographs: Family, undated (Box 935.6)
- Smith College Scrapbook, 1878-1882 (Box 935.8)
  Contains dance cards, class schedules, invitations, cards, and other college-related ephemera.